<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Jonas Wallin, mathematical statistics</title><link>/</link><description></description><atom:link href="/feeds/bolin.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><item><title>Efficient adaptive MCMC through precision estimation</title><link>/articles/2016/04/efficient-adaptive-mcmc-through-precision-estimation/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We used an efficent algorithm to online compute the Cholesky factor of the precision matrix.
Using a sparisty structure of the conditional depence structure, this results in a very efficent AMCMC method. The algorithm is also parallelizable. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matlab code is avialbe at: &lt;a href="http://jonaswallin.github.io/articles/2015/05/precision-based-mala-and-mhrw/"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Bolin</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2016-04-06:articles/2016/04/efficient-adaptive-mcmc-through-precision-estimation/</guid><category>article</category><category>AMCMC</category><category>MH</category><category>MCMC</category><category>MALA</category></item><item><title>Spatially adaptive covariance tapering</title><link>/articles/2016/04/spatially-adaptive-covariance-tapering/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Using a set of simple compactly supported non-stationary covariance functions, 
combined with a new method for choosing spatially varying taper ranges, we achive an efficent adaptive tapring.
We also explore it for parameter estimation, but here just blocking data is better.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Bolin</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2016-04-06:articles/2016/04/spatially-adaptive-covariance-tapering/</guid><category>article</category><category>tapering</category><category>spatial statistics</category></item><item><title>LGFM model</title><link>/articles/2014/03/lgfm-model/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We introduce the the latent Gaussian random field mixture (LGFM) models.
The model class combines the discrete Markov random fields (MRFs) with latent Gaussian random field models and can be used for simultaneous segmentation, noise reduction, and interpolation of spatial data. The latent model is defined as a mixture of several, possibly multivariate, Gaussian random fields, and which of the fields that is observed at each location is modeled using a discrete random field, such as a discrete MRF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an application we study the noise reduction ability on a magnetic resonance imaging data. In a simulation study (not in the preprint) we also study the ability to detect discontinouties in mean functions of latent Gaussian process. The model preforms much better then the regular latent Gaussian model in recustring the latent fields in both the simulation study and in the noise reduction of the real data. &lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Bolin</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2014-03-25:articles/2014/03/lgfm-model/</guid><category>MRF model</category><category>latent Gaussian process</category><category>estimation</category><category>kriging</category><category>mri imaging</category></item></channel></rss>