<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jonas Wallin, mathematical statistics</title><link>/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><item><title>Infinite dimensional AMCMC for Gaussian processes</title><link>/articles/2018/04/infinite-dimensional-amcmc-for-gaussian-processes/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We have develop adaptive versions of the preconditioned Crank–Nicolson Langevin (pCNL) algorithm,
which can be viewed as an infinite dimensional version of the well known Metropolis-adjusted
Langevin algorithm (MALA) algorithm for Gaussian processes.  We also use adaptive methods tailored for infinite dimensions.
The figure above shows the estimation of the eigenvalues if one uses infinite dimensional estimation methods or regular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matlab code is available at: &lt;a href="https://github.com/JonasWallin/Infinite_dimensional_adaptive_MCMC"&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Wallin</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:,2018-04-17:articles/2018/04/infinite-dimensional-amcmc-for-gaussian-processes/</guid><category>article</category><category>AMCMC</category><category>MCMC</category><category>Crank–Nicolson Langevin</category></item><item><title>Linear Mixed-Effects Models for Non-Gaussian Repeated Measurement Dataprocesses</title><link>/articles/2018/04/linear-mixed-effects-models-for-non-gaussian-repeated-measurement-dataprocesses/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We consider the analysis of continuous repeated measurement outcomes that are collected through time, also known as longitudinal data. A standard framework for analysing data of this kind is a linear Gaussian mixed-effects model within which the outcome variable can be decomposed into fixed-effects, time-invariant and time-varying random-effects, and measurement noise. We develop methodology that, for the first time, allows any combination of these stochastic components to be non-Gaussian, using multivariate Normal variance-mean mixtures. We estimate parameters by max- imum likelihood, implemented with a novel, computationally efficient stochastic gradient algorithm. We obtain standard error estimates by inverting the observed Fisher-information matrix, and obtain the predictive distributions for the random-effects in both filtering (conditioning on past and current data) and smoothing (conditioning on all data) contexts. To implement these procedures, we intro- duce an R package, ngme. We re-analyse two data-sets, from cystic fibrosis and nephrology research, that were previously analysed using Gaussian linear mixed effects models.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Wallin</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:,2018-04-17:articles/2018/04/linear-mixed-effects-models-for-non-gaussian-repeated-measurement-dataprocesses/</guid><category>article</category><category>Mixed effect</category><category>Non Gaussian</category><category>Levy processes</category><category>stochastic gradient estimation</category></item><item><title>non-Gaussian Matern Fields</title><link>/articles/2013/07/non-gaussian-matern-fields/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In this article, we exaim how to preform estimation and predicition on a certain type of continous non Gaussian random fields models.
The article is an application extension of the article &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1206.0622"&gt;Bolin 2013&lt;/a&gt; (now published in SJS).
We extend the models in the article, by adding measurement noise and covariates; the estimation
is done through a MCEM algorithm. 
We also test how the models preform on a real data set with precipitation over the US; comparing the model to the
standard Gaussian and transformed Gaussian models. The conlusion for this data is that the models works well
but we need to incorporate covariates into the variance, since the mean and variance of the data is clearly linked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R code is available at: &lt;a href="https://bitbucket.org/davidbolin/lang"&gt;Lang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Extensions:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next planned extension is to change from MCEM to other stochastic estimation methods; There are two main reasons
    for this, first hopefully we can improve the speed of the algorithm, secondly we hope it allowes for more advanced models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expanding the model for regular grids; where a more rich noise class can be studied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Wallin</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:,2013-07-24:articles/2013/07/non-gaussian-matern-fields/</guid><category>article</category><category>generalized Hyperbolic disribution</category><category>MCEM</category><category>SPDEs</category><category>spatial</category><category>precipitation</category></item><item><title>LeaveOneOut</title><link>/articles/2013/06/leaveoneout/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In this article, we study an estimator of the location parameters ($\delta$) when the
density grows as $cx^{-1}$ when $x \rightarrow 0$. The idea is simply to remove the density ,$f(x_i-\delta)$, coming from observation $i=\argmin_j |x_j-\delta|$ from the log likelihood to get the LeaveOneOut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
    L(\delta) = \sum_{j \neq i} \log(f(x_i-\delta)).
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Extensions:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The optimal rate of convergence it not achived. Is this due to 
the method is lacking, or due to the proof is lacking?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We study this class of densities manly beacuse that the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Variance-gamma_distribution"&gt;Generalized Laplace distribution&lt;/a&gt; (Variance Gamma) is contained in the class. It remains to show that consisteny for the LeaveOneOut likelihood for all the parameters of the distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Wallin</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:,2013-06-14:articles/2013/06/leaveoneout/</guid><category>consistent estimator</category><category>unbounded density</category><category>article</category><category>Laplace distribution</category></item></channel></rss>